Guide to the Theodore Schapiro Papers and Photographs TAM.217
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Theodore Schapiro Papers and Photographs
1913-1956
TAM.217
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
0.25 linear feet in one manuscript box
Theodore Schapiro (1898-1998), was a political activist and the last director of the Rand School of Social Science (1943-56). This collection consists of biographical matter, business correspondence (including several letters from Norman Thomas, and individual letters from Erich Fromm, Nina Hillquit, and Sidney Hook), documents from the Rand School's Institute of Social Studies, and photographs.
Schapiro, Theodore, 1898-1998
Historical/Biographical Note
Theodore Schapiro (1898-1998) was a political activist and the last director of the Rand School of Social Science (1943-56). His early training in art and industrial design at Cooper Union, the Art Students' League, and the Beaux Arts Institute of Design led to a career in industrial design. He joined the Socialist Party early in his life and assisted in planning the Party's platform for Norman Thomas' presidential bid in 1940. He served as an organizer for the Textile Workers Union as well as other unions, and he taught adult education classes for them and for the International Ladies' Garment Workers Union. During the 1930s he was employed by the Works Progress Administration's Federal Arts Project.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Provenance unknown, but Theodore Schapiro likely sent a gift of photographs and papers in 1998. The accession numbers associated with this gift are NPA.1999.017 and 1999.023.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
The files are grouped into two series; folders are arranged alphabetically by topic within each series.
Series I: Papers, 1913-1956
Series II: Photographs, 1914-1954
Scope and Contents note
This collection consists of biographical matter, business correspondence (including several letters from Norman Thomas, and individual letters from Erich Fromm, Nina Hillquit, and Sidney Hook), documents from the Rand School's Institute of Social Studies, and photographs.
Hillquit, Nina; Hook, Sidney, 1902-1989; Rand School of Social Science. Institute of Social Studies.; Rand School of Social Science.; Schapiro, Miriam; Schapiro, Theodore, 1898-1998; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Adult education |z New York (State) |z New York.; Biography files.; Black-and-white photographs.; Correspondence.; Jewish socialists |z United States.; Records (documents); Socialism |z United States.; Socialists |z United States.; Working class |x Education |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Papers, 1913-1956
  - Biographical, 1913-1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Commie's Lament or, Custer's Last Stand" (poem/lyrics?), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1931-1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Printed Ephmera, Miscellaneous, circa 1936, 1957, 1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rand School of Social Science/Institute ot Social Studies, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - WPA - Federal Art Project, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Photographs, 1914-circa 1959
  Scope and Content Note
  Fifty-six black and white photographs, including a few portraits of Schapiro and of Schapiro speaking, events at the Rand School of Social Science (classroom and lecture images; individuals include Sidney Hook), and Socialist Party-related events. The latter images include what appear to be campaign workers for one or more of Meyer London's campaigns for Congress for New York State's 12th congressional district (between 1914 and 1920), with an interior splashed with Socialist Party campaign posters; one image includes London himself.
  - Theodore Schapiro - Portraits, circa 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Rand School of Social Science, circa 1940-circa 1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Socialist Party, circa 1914-circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified Events, circa 1940-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)